<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="OblongBox2.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//ELEMENTS TEI Lite XML ver. 1//EN"
"teixlite.dtd" [<!ENTITY mdash "-"> <!ENTITY rsquo "'"> <!ENTITY lsquo "'">]>
<TEI.2 id="The Oblong Box">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>&quot;The Oblong Box&quot;</title>
        <author>Edgar Allan Poe</author>
          <principal>Jerry Kennedy</principal>
          <respStmt>
              <name>Jordan Von Cannon</name>
              <resp>Literary Scholarship</resp>
          </respStmt>
          <respStmt>
              <name>Jackie Thornton</name>
              <resp>Electronic Retrieval and Markup</resp>
          </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition>Second</edition>
            <respStmt>
                <name>Jackie Thornton</name>
                <resp>Electronic Retrieval and Markup</resp>
            </respStmt>
        </editionStmt>
        <extent>
            <seg type="size"></seg>
            <seg type="format">XML File</seg>
            <seg type="location"></seg>
        </extent>
      <publicationStmt>
          <distributor>
              <address>
                <addrLine>
              <name type="organisation"></name>
                 </addrLine>
                      <addrLine></addrLine>
                       <addrLine>
                          <name type="place"></name>
                        </addrLine>
                        <addrLine></addrLine>
                        <addrLine></addrLine>
                    </address>
          </distributor>
          <availability status="restricted">
              <p></p>
          </availability>
          <date></date>
          <pubPlace></pubPlace>
          <publisher rend="italic"></publisher>
          <date></date>
      </publicationStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note>APC Project</note>
        </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
          <bibl><title>The Oblong Box</title> <author>Edgar Allan Poe</author><publisher>Broadway Journal 2:345-352</publisher>
              <date>December 13, 1845</date></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
        <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><title>The Edgar Allan Poe Society of Baltimore</title> <author>Jeffrey A. Savoye
            </author> <date>September 14, 2011</date></bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
          <editorialDecl>
              <p></p>
          </editorialDecl>
          <refsDecl>
              <p></p>
          </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc><textClass><keywords>
          <list><head>Geographic Names</head>
              <item>Charleston, SC</item>
              <item>New York</item></list>
      </keywords>
          <keywords><list><head>Literary Types</head>
              <item>Satire</item>
              <item>Allegory</item>
              <item>Metaphor</item>
              <item>Political Commentary</item>
          </list>
          </keywords>
      </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
          <change>
              <date></date>
              <respStmt>
                  <name></name>
                  <resp></resp>
              </respStmt>
              <item></item>
          </change>
          <change>
              <date></date>
              <respStmt>
                  <name></name>
                  <resp></resp>
              </respStmt>
              <item></item>
          </change>
          <change>
              <date></date>
              <respStmt>
                  <name></name>
                  <resp></resp>
              </respStmt>
              <item></item>
          </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">&quot;Oblong Box&quot;</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
          <docAuthor>Edgar Allan Poe</docAuthor>
          <docDate></docDate>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    <body>
        <p><soCalled>SOME</soCalled> years ago, I engaged passage from <name type="place">Charleston, S. C.</name>, to the city of <name type="place">New York</name>, in the
            fine packet-ship <q><name type="Historical Allusion" key="BoxHisAll1"><rs type="Jingoism" key="BoxJingo1">Independence</rs></name>,</q>
          <name type="Historical Allusion" key="BoxHisAll2">Captain Hardy</name>. We were to sail on the <rs type="date">fifteenth of the month (June,)</rs> weather permitting; 
            and, on the fourteenth, I went on board to arrange some matters in my state-room.</p>

        <p>I found that we were to have a great many passengers, including a more than usual number of ladies. On the list were
            several of my acquaintances; and among other names, I was rejoiced to see that of <name type="person">Mr. Cornelius Wyatt</name>, a young artist, for whom I
            entertained feelings of warm friendship. He had been with me a fellow-student at <name type="place">C&mdash;&mdash; University</name>, where we were very much
            together. He had the ordinary temperament of <rs type="Intertextuality" key="BoxIntertext1">genius</rs>, and was a compound of misanthropy, sensibility, and enthusiasm. To these qualities
            he united the warmest and truest heart which ever beat in a human bosom.</p>

        <p>I observed that his name was carded upon <emph rend="italic">three</emph> state-rooms; and, upon again referring to the list of passengers,
            I found that he had engaged passage for himself, wife, and two sisters &mdash; his own. The state-rooms were sufficiently roomy, and
            each had two berths, one above the other. These berths, to be sure, were so exceedingly narrow as to be insufficient for more than one
            person; still, I could not comprehend why there were three state-rooms for these four persons. <rs type="Intertextuality" key="BoxIntertext2">I was, just at that epoch, in one
            of those moody frames of mind which make a man abnormally inquisitive about trifles</rs>; and I confess, with shame, that I busied myself in
            a variety of ill-bred and preposterous conjectures about this matter of the supernumerary state-room. It was no business of mine, to be
            sure; but with none the less pertinacity did I occupy myself in attempts to resolve the enigma. At last I reached a conclusion which
            wrought in me great wonder why I had not arrived at it before. <q>It is a servant, of course,</q> I said; <q>what a fool I
            am, not sooner to have thought of so obvious a solution!</q> And then I again repaired to the list &mdash; but here I saw distinctly
            that no servant was to come with the party; although, in fact, it had been the original design to bring one &mdash; for the words
           <q>and servant</q> had been first written and then overscored. <q>Oh, extra baggage to be sure,</q> I now said to myself
           &mdash; <q>something he wishes not to be put in the hold &mdash; something to be kept under his own eye &mdash; ah, I have it
           &mdash; a painting or so &mdash; and this is what he has been bargaining about with <name type="person"><rs type="Racism" key="BoxRace1">Nicolino</rs></name>,
            <rs type="Racism" key="BoxRace2">the Italian Jew</rs>.</q> This idea satisfied me, and I dismissed my curiosity for the nonce.</p>

        <p><name type="person">Wyatt&rsquo;s</name> two sisters I knew very well, and most amiable and clever girls they were. His wife he had newly married,
            and I had never yet seen her. He had often talked about her in my presence, however, and in his usual style of enthusiasm. 
            <rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty1">He described
            her as of surpassing <rs type="Female Ideal of Era">beauty, wit, and accomplishment</rs>. I was, therefore, quite anxious to make her acquaintance.</rs></p>

        <p> On the day in which I visited the ship, (the fourteenth,) <name type="person">Wyatt</name> and party were also to visit it &mdash; so the captain
            informed me &mdash; and I waited on board an hour longer than I had designed, in hope of being presented to the bride; but then an
            apology came. <q><name type="person">Mrs. W.</name> was a little indisposed, and would decline coming on board until to-morrow, at the hour of sailing.</q></p>

        <p> <rs type="date">The morrow having arrived</rs>, I was going from my hotel to the wharf, when <name type="person">Captain Hardy</name> met me and said that,
           <q>owing to circumstances,</q> (a stupid but convenient phrase,) <q>he rather thought the &lsquo;<rs type="Jingoism" key="BoxJingo1">Independence</rs>&rsquo; would
             not sail for a day or two, and that when all was ready, he would send up and let me know.</q> This I thought strange, for there was a
           stiff southerly breeze; but as <q>the circumstances</q> were not forthcoming, although I pumped for them with much perseverance,
            I had nothing to do but to return home and digest my impatience at leisure.</p>

        <p>I did not receive the expected message from the captain for <rs type="date">nearly a week</rs>. It came at length, however, and I
            immediately went on board. The ship was crowded with passengers, and everything was in the bustle attendant upon making sail.
            <name type="person">Wyatt&rsquo;s</name> party arrived in about ten minutes after myself. There were the two sisters, the bride, and the artist &mdash; the latter
            in one of his customary fits of moody misanthropy. I was too well used to these, however, to pay them any special attention. He did not
            even introduce me to his wife; &mdash; this courtesy devolving, per force, upon his sister <name type="person">Marian</name> &mdash; 
            <rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty2">a very sweet and intelligent girl</rs>, who, in a few hurried words, made us acquainted.</p>

        <p><name type="person">Mrs. Wyatt</name> had been closely veiled; and when she raised her veil, in acknowledging my bow, I confess that I was very
            profoundly astonished. I should have been much more so, however, had not long experience advised me not to trust, with too <sic>inplicit</sic>
            [[<corr>implicit</corr>]] a reliance, the enthusiastic descriptions of my friend, the artist, when indulging in comments upon <rs type="Intertextuality" key="BoxIntertext3"><rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty1">the loveliness of
            woman</rs></rs>. When beauty was the theme, I well knew with what facility he soared into the regions of the purely ideal.</p>

        <p><rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty3">The truth is, I could not help regarding <name type="person">Mrs. Wyatt</name> as a decidedly plain-looking woman. If not positively ugly, she was
            not, I think, very far from it. She was dressed, however, in exquisite taste &mdash; and then I had no doubt that she had captivated my
            friend&rsquo;s heart by the more enduring graces of the intellect and soul.</rs> She said very few words, and passed at once into her
            state-room with <name type="person">Mr. W.</name></p>

        <p>My old inquisitiveness now returned. There was no servant &mdash; that was a settled point. I looked,
            therefore, for the extra baggage. After some delay, a cart arrived at the wharf, with an <rs type="PlotConflict">oblong pine box</rs>, which was everything that
            <sic>seeemed</sic> [[<corr>seemed</corr>]] to be expected. Immediately upon its arrival we made sail, and in a short time were <rs type="LiteraryAllusion"><rs type="HistoricalAllusion">safely over the bar</rs></rs> and standing
            out to sea.</p>

        <p>The box in question was, as I say, oblong. It was about six feet in length by two and a half in breadth; &mdash; <rs type="PlotConflict">I
            observed it attentively, and like to be precise</rs>.  Now this shape was peculiar; and no sooner had I seen it, than I took credit to
            myself for the accuracy of my guessing. I had reached the conclusion, it will be remembered, that the extra baggage of my friend, the
            artist, would prove to be pictures, or at least a picture; for I knew he had been for several weeks in conference with 
            <name><rs type="Racism" key="BoxRace1">Nicolino</rs></name>: &mdash;
            and <rs type="Parody">now here was a box which, from its shape, could possibly contain nothing in the world but a copy of <name type="person">Leonardo&rsquo;s</name>
          <q><rs type="Religion" key="BoxRel1">Last Supper</rs>;</q> and a copy of this very
            <q><rs type="Religion" key="BoxRel1">Last Supper</rs>,</q> done by <name type="person">Rubini</name> the younger, at <name type="place">Florence</name>, I had known, for
            some time, to be in the possession of <name><rs type="Racism" key="BoxRace1">Nicolino</rs></name></rs>. This point, therefore, I considered as sufficiently settled. I chuckled excessively when
            I thought of <rs type="Intertextuality">my acumen</rs>. It was the first time I had ever known <name type="person">Wyatt</name> to keep from me any of his artistical secrets; but here he
            evidently intended <rs type="Intertextuality">to steal a march upon me</rs>, and smuggle a fine picture to <name type="place">New York</name>, under my very nose; expecting me to know nothing of
            the matter. I resolved to <rs>quiz him</rs> well, now and hereafter.</p>

        <p>One thing, however, annoyed me not a little. The box did not go into the extra state-room. It was deposited in
            <name type="person">Wyatt&rsquo;s</name> own; and there, too, it remained, occupying very nearly the whole of the floor &mdash; no doubt to the exceeding
            discomfort of the artist and his wife; &mdash; this the more especially as the tar or paint with which it was lettered in sprawling
            capitals, emitted a strong, disagreeable, and, to my fancy, <rs type="PlotConflict">a peculiarly disgusting odor</rs>. On the lid were painted the words
            &mdash; <q><name type="person">Mrs. Adelaide Curtis</name>, <name type="place">Albany, New York</name>. Charge of <name type="person">Cornelius Wyatt</name>, Esq. This side up. To be handled with
              care.</q></p>

        <p>Now, I was aware that <name type="person">Mrs. Adelaide Curtis</name>, of <name type="place">Albany</name>, was the artist&rsquo;s wife&rsquo;s mother; &mdash; but then I
            looked upon the whole address as <rs type="Intertextuality">a mystification</rs>, intended especially for myself. I made up my mind, of course, that the box and
            contents would never get farther north than the studio of my misanthropic friend, in 
            <rs type="Allusion" key="BoxAll1"><name type="place">Chambers Street, New York</name></rs>.</p>

        <p>For the <rs type="date">first three or four days</rs> we had fine weather, although the wind was dead ahead; having chopped round to the
            northward, immediately upon our losing sight of the coast. The passengers were, consequently, in high spirits, and disposed to be
            social. I must except, however, <name type="person">Wyatt</name> and his sisters, who behaved stiffly, and, I could not help thinking,
            uncourteously to the rest of the party.  <name type="person">Wyatt&rsquo;s</name> conduct I did not so much regard. <rs type="PlotConflict">He was gloomy, even beyond his usual
            habit &mdash; in fact he was morose &mdash; but in him I was prepared for eccentricity. 
            <rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty2">For the sisters, however, I could make no excuse. They secluded themselves in their state-rooms during the greater part of the passage, and absolutely refused, although I
            repeatedly urged them, to hold communication with any person on board.</rs></rs></p>

        <p><name type="person">Mrs. Wyatt</name> herself was far more agreeable. That is to say, she was chatty; and to be chatty is no slight
            recommendation at sea. She became excessively intimate with most of the ladies; and, to my profound astonishment, evinced no
            equivocal disposition to coquet with the men. She amused us all very much. I say <q>amused</q> &mdash; and scarcely know
            how to explain myself. 
            <rs type="Beauty" key="BoxBeauty3">The truth is, I soon found that <name type="person">Mrs. W.</name> was far oftener laughed at than with. The gentlemen said
           little about her; but the ladies, in a little while, pronounced her <q>a good-hearted thing, <rs type="Women">rather indifferent-looking, totally
             uneducated, and decidedly vulgar</rs>.</q>  The great wonder was, how <name type="person">Wyatt</name> had been entrapped into such a match.</rs> Wealth was the general
           solution &mdash; but this I knew to be no solution at all; for <name type="person">Wyatt</name> had told me that she neither brought him a dollar nor had any
           expectations from any source whatever. <q>He had married,</q> he said, <q>for love, and for love only; and his bride was far
             more than worthy of his love.</q> When I thought of these expressions, on the part of my friend, I confess that I felt indescribably
            puzzled. Could it be possible that he was taking leave of his senses? What else could I think? He, so refined, so intellectual,
            so fastidious, with so exquisite a perception of the faulty, and so keen an appreciation of the beautiful! To be sure, the lady seemed
            especially fond of him &mdash; particularly so in his absence &mdash; when she made herself ridiculous by frequent quotations of
            what had been said by her <q>beloved husband, <name type="person">Mr. Wyatt.</name></q> The word <q>husband</q> seemed forever &mdash; to use one of
           her own delicate expressions &mdash; forever <q>on the tip of her tongue.</q> In the meantime, it was observed by all on board,
            that he avoided her in the most pointed manner, and, for the most part, shut himself up alone in his state-room, where, in fact,
            he might have been said to live altogether, leaving his wife at full liberty to amuse herself as she thought best, in the public society
            of the main cabin.</p>

        <p>My conclusion, from what I saw and heard, was, that, the artist, by some unaccountable freak of fate, or perhaps in
            some fit of enthusiastic and fanciful passion, had been induced to unite himself with a person altogether beneath him, and that the
            natural result, entire and speedy disgust, had ensued. I pitied him from the bottom of my heart &mdash; but could not, for that reason,
            quite forgive his incommunicativeness in the matter of the 
            <q><rs type="Religion" key="BoxRel1">Last Supper</rs>.</q> For this I resolved to have my revenge.</p>

        <p>One day he came upon deck, and, taking his arm as had been my wont, I sauntered with him backwards and forwards. His
            gloom, however, (which I considered quite natural under the circumstances,) seemed entirely unabated. He said little, and <sic>tha</sic> [[<corr>that</corr>]]
            moodily, and with evident effort. I ventured a jest or two, and he made a sickening attempt at a smile. Poor fellow! &mdash; as I
            thought of his wife, I wondered that he could have heart to put on even the semblance of mirth. <rs type="PlotConflict">At last I ventured a home thrust.
            I determined to commence a series of covert insinuations, or innuendoes, about the oblong box &mdash; just to let him perceive,
            gradually, that I was not altogether the butt, or victim, of his little bit of pleasant mystification</rs>. My first observation was
            by way of opening a masked battery. I said something about the <q>peculiar shape of that box;</q> and, as I spoke the
            words, I smiled knowingly, winked, and touched him gently with my fore-finger in the ribs.</p>

        <p>The manner in which <name>Wyatt</name> received this harmless pleasantry, convinced me, at once, that he was mad. At first he stared
            at me as if he found it impossible to comprehend the witticism of my remark; but as its point seemed slowly to make its way into his
            brain, his eyes in the same proportion, seemed protruding from their sockets. Then he grew very red &mdash; then hideously pale &mdash;
            then, as if highly amused with what I had insinuated, he began a loud and boisterous laugh, which, to my astonishment, he kept up, with
            gradually increasing vigor, for ten minutes or more. In conclusion, he fell flat and heavily upon the deck. When I ran to uplift him, to
            all appearance he was <rs>dead</rs>.</p>

        <p>I called assistance, and, with much difficulty, we brought him to himself. Upon reviving he spoke incoherently for some
            time. At length we bled him and put him to bed. The next morning he was quite recovered, so far as regarded his mere bodily health. Of
            his mind I say nothing, of course. I avoided him during the rest of the passage, by advice of the captain, who seemed to coincide with
            me altogether in my views of his insanity, but cautioned me to say nothing on this head to any person on board.</p>

        <p>Several circumstances occurred immediately after this fit of <name>Wyatt&rsquo;s</name>, which contributed to heighten the curiosity
            with which I was already possessed. Among other things, this: I had been <rs type="Intertextuality">nervous</rs> &mdash; drank too much strong <hi>green tea</hi>, and slept ill
            at night &mdash; in fact, for two nights I could not be properly said to sleep at all. Now, my state-room opened into the main cabin, or
            dining-room, as did those of all the single men on board. <name>Wyatt&rsquo;s</name> three rooms were in the after-cabin, which was separated from
            the main one by a slight sliding door, never locked even at night. As we were almost constantly on a wind, and the breeze was not a
            little stiff, the ship heeled to leeward very considerably; and whenever her starboard side was to leeward, the sliding door between the
            cabins slid open, and so remained, nobody taking the trouble to get up and shut it. But my berth was in such a position, that when my
            own state-room door was open, as well as the sliding door in question, (and my own door was always open on account of the heat,)
            I could see into the after-cabin quite distinctly, and just at that portion of it, too, where were situated the state-rooms of <name>Mr. 
              Wyatt</name>. Well, during two nights (not consecutive) while I lay awake, I clearly saw <name>Mrs. W.</name>, about eleven o&rsquo;clock upon each
           night, steal cautiously from the state-room of <name>Mr. W.</name>, and enter the extra room, where she remained until daybreak, when she was called
            by her husband and went back. That they were virtually separated was clear. They had separate apartments &mdash; no doubt in
            contemplation of a more permanent divorce; and here, after all, I thought, was the mystery of the extra state-room.</p>

        <p>There was another circumstance, too, which interested me much. During the two wakeful nights in question, and
            immediately after the disappearance of <name>Mrs. Wyatt</name> into the extra state-room, I was attracted by certain singular, cautious, subdued
            noises in that of her husband. After listening to them for some time, with thoughtful attention, I at length succeeded perfectly in
            translating their import. They were sounds occasioned by the artist in prying open the oblong box, by means of a chisel and mallet
            &mdash; the latter being apparently muffled, or deadened, by some soft woollen or cotton substance in which its head was enveloped.</p>

        <p>In this manner I fancied I could distinguish the precise moment when he fairly disengaged the lid &mdash; also, that I
            could determine when he removed it altogether, and when he deposited it upon the lower berth in his room; this latter point I knew, for
            example, by certain slight taps which the lid made in striking against the wooden edges of the berth, as he endeavored to lay it down
            very gently &mdash; there being no room for it on the floor. After this there was a dead stillness, and I heard nothing more,
            upon either [column 2:] occasion, until nearly daybreak; unless, perhaps, I may mention a low sobbing, or murmuring sound, so
            very much suppressed as to be nearly inaudible &mdash; if, indeed, the whole of this latter noise were not rather produced by my own
            imagination. I say it seemed to resemble sobbing or sighing &mdash; but, of course, <rs type="PlotConflict">it could not have been either</rs>. I rather think
            it was a ringing in my own ears. <name>Mr. Wyatt</name>, no doubt, according to custom, was merely giving the rein to one of his hobbies &mdash;
            indulging in one of his fits of artistic enthusiasm. He had opened his oblong box, in order to feast his eyes on the pictorial treasure
            within. There was nothing in this however, to make him sob. I repeat, therefore, that it must have been simply a freak of my own
            fancy, distempered by good <name>Captain Hardy&rsquo;s</name> green tea. Just before dawn, on each of the two nights of which I speak, I distinctly
            heard <name>Mr. Wyatt</name> replace the lid upon the oblong box, and force the nails into their old places, by means of the muffled mallet. Having
            done this, he issued from his state-room, fully dressed, and proceeded to call <name>Mrs. W.</name> from hers.</p>

        <p> <rs type="Date">We had been at sea seven days</rs>, and were now off <name type="place">Cape Hatteras</name>, when there came on a tremendously heavy blow from the
            southwest. We were, in a measure, prepared for it, however, as the weather had been holding out threats for some time. Everything was
            made snug, alow and aloft; and as the wind steadily freshened, we lay to, at length, under spanker and foretopsail, both double-reefed.</p>
        <p> In this trim, we rode safely enough for <rs type="date">forty-eight hours</rs> &mdash; the ship proving herself an excellent sea<sic>-</sic>boat,
            in many respects, and shipping no water of any consequence. At the end of this period, however, the gale had freshened into a hurricane,
            and our after-sail split into ribbons, bringing us so much in the trough of the water that we shipped several prodigious seas, one
            immediately after the other. By this accident we lost three men overboard, with the caboose, and nearly the whole of the larboard
            bulwarks. Scarcely had we recovered our senses, before the foretopsail went into shreds, when we got up a storm stay-sail, and with this
            did pretty well for some hours, the ship heading the seas much more steadily than before. </p>

        <p> The gale still held on, however, and we saw no signs of its abating. The rigging was found to be ill-fitted, and
            greatly strained; and on the <rs type="Date">third day of the blow</rs>, about five in the afternoon, our mizzen-mast, in a heavy lurch to windward, went by
            the board. For an hour or more, we tried in vain to get rid of it, on account of the prodigious rolling of the ship; and, before we had
            succeeded, the carpenter came aft and announced four feet of water in the hold. To add to our dilemma, we found the pumps choked and
            nearly useless.</p>

        <p>All was now confusion and despair &mdash; but an effort was made to lighten the ship by throwing overboard as much of
            her cargo as could be reached, and by cutting away the two masts that remained. This we at last accomplished &mdash; but we were still
            unable to do anything at the pumps; and, in the meantime, the leak gained on us very fast.</p>

        <p>At sundown, the gale had sensibly diminished in violence, and, as the sea went down with it, we still entertained faint
            hopes of saving ourselves in the boats. At eight, P. M., the clouds broke away to windward, and we had the advantage of a full moon
            &mdash; a piece of good fortune which served wonderfully to cheer our drooping spirits.</p>

        <p>After incredible labor we succeeded, at length, in getting the long-boat over the side without material accident, and
            into this we crowded the whole of the crew and most of the passengers. This party made off immediately, and, after undergoing much
            suffering, finally arrived, in safety, at 
            <rs type="Jingoism" key="Jingo2">Ocracoke Inlet</rs>, <rs type="Date">on the third day after the wreck</rs>.</p>

        <p>Fourteen passengers, with the Captain, remained on board, resolving to trust their fortunes to the jolly-boat at the
            stern. We lowered it without difficulty, although it was only by a miracle that we prevented it from swamping as it touched the water.
            It contained, when afloat, <rs>the captain and his wife, <name>Mr. Wyatt</name> and party, a Mexican officer, wife, four children, and myself, with a
            <rs type="Racism" key="Race2">negro</rs> valet.</rs></p>

        <p>We had no room, of course, for anything except a few positively necessary instruments, some provisions, and the clothes
            upon our backs. No one had thought of even attempting to save anything more. What must have been the astonishment of all then, when
            having proceeded a few fathoms from the ship, <name>Mr. Wyatt</name> stood up in the stern-sheets, and coolly demanded of <name>Captain Hardy</name> that the boat
            should be put back for the purpose of taking in his oblong box!</p>

        <p><q>Sit down, <name>Mr. Wyatt</name>,</q> replied the captain, somewhat sternly; <q>you will capsize us if you do not sit
           quite still. Our gunwale is almost in the water now.</q></p>

        <p><q>The box!</q> vociferated <name>Mr. Wyatt</name>, still standing &mdash; <q>the box, I say! <name>Captain Hardy</name>, you cannot,
            you will not refuse me. Its weight will be but a trifle &mdash; it is nothing &mdash; mere nothing. By the mother who bore you
            &mdash; for the love of Heaven &mdash; by your hope of salvation, I implore you to put back for the box!</q></p>

        <p>The captain, for a moment, seemed touched by the earnest appeal of the artist, but he regained his stern composure, and
          merely said &mdash;</p>

        <p>
          <q><name>Mr. Wyatt</name>, you are mad. I cannot listen to you. Sit down, I say, or you will swamp the boat. Stay &mdash;
            hold him &mdash; seize him! &mdash; he is about to spring overboard! There &mdash; I knew it &mdash; he is over!</q>
        </p>
        <p> As the captain said this, <name>Mr. Wyatt</name>, in fact, sprang from the boat, and, as we were yet in the lee of the wreck,
            succeeded, by almost superhuman exertion, in getting hold of a rope which hung from the fore-chains. In another moment he was on board,
            and rushing frantically down into the cabin.</p>

        <p>In the meantime, we had been swept astern of the ship, and being quite out of her lee, were at the mercy of the
            tremendous sea which was still running. We made a determined effort to put back, but our little boat was like a feather in the breath of
            the tempest. We saw at a glance that the doom of the unfortunate artist was sealed.</p>

        <p>As our distance from the wreck rapidly increased, the madman (for as such only could we regard him) was seen to emerge
            from the companion-way, up which by dint of a strength that appeared gigantic, he dragged, bodily, the oblong box. While we gazed in the
            extremity of astonishment, <rs
            type="Allusion" key="All2"
            >he passed, rapidly, several turns of a three-inch rope, first around the box and then around his body. In
            another instant both body and box were in the sea &mdash; disappearing suddenly, at once and forever.</rs></p>

        <p>We lingered awhile sadly upon our oars, with our eyes riveted upon the spot. At length we pulled away. The silence
          remained unbroken for an hour. Finally, I hazarded a remark.</p>

        <p>
          <q>Did you observe, Captain, how suddenly they sank? Was not that an exceedingly singular thing? I confess that I
            entertained some feeble hope of his final deliverance, when I saw him lash himself to the box, and commit himself to the sea.</q>
        </p>

        <p><q>They sank as a matter of course,</q> replied the Captain, <q>and that like a shot. They will soon rise
           again, however &mdash; <rs
              type="Death" key="Death1">but not till the salt melts.</rs></q></p>

        <p><q><rs type="Death" key="Death1">The salt!</rs></q> I ejaculated.</p>

        <p><q>Hush!</q> said the Captain, pointing to the wife and sisters of the deceased. <q>We must talk of these
           things at some more appropriate time.</q></p>

        <p> &mdash;&mdash;</p>

        <p>We suffered much, and made a narrow escape; but fortune [column 2:] befriended us, as well as our mates
            in the long<sic>-</sic>boat. We landed, in fine, more dead than alive, after four days of intense distress, upon the beach opposite <rs
            type="Jingoism" key="Jingo2">Roanoke
            Island</rs>. We remained here a week, were not ill-treated by the wreckers, and at length obtained a passage to New York.</p>

        <p>About a month after the loss of the <q><rs type="Jingoism" key="Jingo1"
            >Independence</rs>,</q> I happened to meet <name>Captain Hardy</name> in Broadway. Our
           conversation turned, naturally, upon the disaster, and especially upon the sad fate of poor <name>Wyatt</name>. I thus learned the following
            particulars.</p>

        <p>The artist had engaged passage for himself, wife, two sisters and a servant. <rs type="Beauty" key="Beauty1">His wife was, indeed, as she had been
            represented, a most lovely, and most accomplished woman.</rs>
          <rs type="Death" key="Death2">On the morning of the fourteenth of June, (the day in which I first visited the
            ship,) the lady suddenly sickened and died.</rs> The young husband was frantic with grief &mdash; but circumstances imperatively forbade the
            deferring his voyage to New York. <rs type="Death" key="Death3">It was necessary to take to her mother the corpse of his adored wife, and on the other hand, the
            universal prejudice which would prevent his doing so openly, was well known. Nine-tenths of the passengers would have abandoned the ship
            rather than take passage with a dead body.</rs></p>

        <p>In this dilemma, <name>Captain Hardy</name> arranged that <rs type="Death" key="Death1">the corpse, being first partially embalmed, and packed, with a large
            quantity of salt, in a box of suitable dimensions, should be conveyed on board as merchandise.</rs> Nothing was to be said of the
            lady&rsquo;s decease; and, <rs type="Beauty" key="Beauty1">as it was well understood that <name>Mr. Wyatt</name> had engaged passage for his wife, it became necessary that some
            person should personate her during the voyage. This the deceased&rsquo;s lady&rsquo;s-maid was easily prevailed on to do. The extra
            state-room, originally engaged for this girl, during her mistress&rsquo; life, was now merely retained. In this state-room the
            pseudo<sic>-</sic>wife slept, of course, every night. In the day-time she performed, to the best of her ability, the part of her mistress
            &mdash; whose person, it had been carefully ascertained, was unknown to any of the passengers on board.</rs></p>

        <p>My own mistake arose, naturally enough, through too careless, too inquisitive, and too impulsive a temperament. But of
            late, it is a rare thing that I sleep soundly at night. <rs type="Death" key="Death4">There is a countenance which haunts me, turn as I will. There is an hysterical
            laugh which will forever ring within my ears.</rs></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
